So welcome to CS 50 week 4 section on memory,
and today we're going to be diving into memory,
pointers,
working with files
and all
to get you more familiar with what C can do
as you prepare for future weeks.
So
if you're new here,
I'm Kelly,
I'm the preceptor here at Harvard,
so I run the college course
and there's my email
if you ever want to contact me.
OK.
So,
what are we gonna be talking about today?
First,
some questions that might have come up for you in lecture
are,
what are these new things called pointers?
How can we become familiar with their syntax?
What is the dynamic memory?
How can we use it?
And how can we read and write data from a file?
So we're going to talk about all of these things here
today,
one by one.
And as a first a preface,
we're going to talk a little bit about hexadecimal notation to get you
um comfortable with seeing
numbers that are written,
addresses that are written
in hexadecimal.
So as a quick review,
Um,
for this week's problem site,
it's
probably gonna be helpful to understand hexadecimal notation,
and hexadecimal numbers are usually indicated by a 0 X in the front.
So when you see 0 X some number,
um,
that is usually indicative of the fact that it's a hexadecimal number.
In hexadecimal,
uh,
unlike base 10,
where you have only
numbers 0 through 9,
you also have
and F,
um,
corresponding with 1011,
1213,
1415,
respectively.
And so hex notation is usually used for representing addresses in memory.
This base 16 system is
um not too
different from what you've seen before and the base
10 system that you use on a daily basis.
Um,
so when you normally see a number like 15
in your head,
you very quickly
are doing the same sort of 10 to 0,
which is
1 times 5,
so I have 5,
and then the 1 is in the 10s place,
so 10 to 1.
And so,
instinctively,
um,
all of us,
when we see
the numbers 15,
we'll think,
OK,
10 + 5 is 15.
Hexadecimal is
the same logic,
but now instead of base 10,
we're using base 16.
And the same goes for binary.
Binary is just the same logic applied to base 2.
And so when you see a hexadecimal number,
um,
for example here we have 0 X and then 3
or 4
bases,
you can
apply the same logic where the
one on the right
will have 16 to 0,
so whatever number there times
1,
and then
whatever numbers in that next
place here
16 to 1
and so on and so forth.
So I'll pause here for any initial questions on hexadecimal.
Couldn't we go to 37 with A to Z or even capitals?
I have 48.
Yeah,
and so
it's really a question of
um what is efficient to represent in memory.
So
Pexadecimal is great because
um it
is pretty compatible with
the number of bits that we usually like to store,
um,
and so as you'll see in a second here,
oops,
um.
The,
for example,
255,
which is
uh a commonly used number to represent RGB values for represented color,
um,
can be easily represented
as um a hexadecimal
number and so,
yeah,
these are just decisions that were made,
uh,
a long time ago but are very compatible with the
like
amount of memory that we're typically using.
OK,
great.
So if I look at a hex value of color and I see other letters like H.
It's a different base system representing color.
Mm.
Yeah,
so,
so that might just be a different
um system that is representing those colors.
But in this
uh piece set,
you'll be using the RGB system of representing colors.
Great question.
OK.
So from that,
we're gonna move on to pointers and talk a little bit more about what that
means,
what these are used for,
and how you might have already actually been using pointers all along,
but you didn't necessarily realize.
OK.
So this
chunk of memory might be something similar to what we've seen in the lecture here
and so this is really just an abstraction of what is going on in your computer,
but hopefully it gives you a bit of a visual
to see
what is really going on here.
And so
you can imagine this is um we have
Um,
a number of bytes in our memory here,
each with an address
arbitrarily starting from 0X08 all the way to 0X1F.
Normally we also don't really care about what these addresses really are,
and they're normally not going to be
this simple when you're actually working in your memory,
but
this is just to demonstrate.
And so,
if
we,
for example,
want to create an integer called N.
We might have that
look a little bit like this.
So if we recall an integer,
um,
takes 4 bytes,
we can see here
that we've allocated
4 bytes
to
this integer and that stores
the value of 4.
And so you can also see that this integer
has an address associated with where it is in memory.
And so,
what is the address of N here?
0 X 08,
as you can see on
this diagram.
And so
we learned some new syntax to represent this
um and if I wanted to get this address.
We can use this ampersand.
So ampersand N
means like the address of N,
and we can see here that that's equal to 0X08.
So next we have this idea,
this new idea of a pointer,
right?
So we have in
P
equals address of N.
So what just happened with this line of code
is that
I created an integer pointer.
So that's
just another variable,
but it's a type integer pointer,
and that's what we can see here with this blue rectangle.
It's called P.
And it's storing the address of N.
So,
we use Ampersand N to get the address of this N variable,
and we're storing it in
our pointer variable P.
OK,
so let's just go over this syntax a little bit more deeply since it's new here.
And so
when you see this first um initializing
statement we're initializing P
in star here is referring to the type.
So it's just another type like in float,
char.
Now we have in star to indicate this is going to be an integer pointer.
This ampersand refers to the address of
a certain
variable,
so we have
ampersan and giving us the address of the integer and.
And then
we can see here
we have another new piece of syntax.
So this star P equals 9.
What's important to note is that the star here
is not
being used the exact same way as the star
we just saw a second ago with this declaration,
right?
So this star means
go to or de-reference
the address stored at P.
So,
look at this address,
0X08,
and then go to that address.
So we're looking now at
0X08,
which is
where N is stored,
and then set that value
to
9.
So I've now changed the value of N
without actually
modifying N itself.
Instead we just modified
it using the pointer.
So again,
this,
this star here
is what we call dereferencing.
Dereference
or go to
the address that is stored in P.
OK,
so
as a summary.
Type star
is a pointer that stores the address of type,
so
type could be an integer,
type could be a character,
type could be a float,
etc.
Ampers X gets the address of
X where X is some variable.
And
X goes to the address stored at the pointer
X.
So in this third scenario,
the X is referring to some sort of pointer that we have,
and goes to the address that is stored at that pointer.
OK,
so before we do this practice,
are there any questions about
pointers?
no
OK.
Um,
How did the address numbers get chosen?
They all seem pretty random.
Yeah,
yeah,
so when you actually go and look at what the
address numbers that are being stored in your computer are,
they do seem pretty random to you,
but the computer has a system
that manages
which parts of memory should be dedicated to
which
pieces of code,
right?
So
if you recall from lecture,
David mentioned
um the heap
and the stack.
The heap is where
um
the memory that you dynamically allocate comes from
and the stack is used for
the local variables that you initialize
and so
the computer does all these things for you.
You don't really necessarily need to think about it yourself,
but
um
it's helpful if you look at lecture to know
which
pieces of memory
and how that's organized so that you know where those numbers are coming from.
Yeah,
great question.
OK,
so let's do a little bit of practice here.
And
see,
we have a little piece of code on the left here
and a little visual of
bits of memory
and so
basically I would encourage you to pause here for a second
and just think at the end of this piece of code running,
what will the final values be for each variable
or pointer?
So I'll give you a second to think.
You can
put your answers in the chat.
Alright,
so hopefully you've thought about this a little bit.
We have some people putting
some
um of their thoughts in the chat here.
So let's walk through it together.
OK,
so line by line,
we're gonna see what's happening to variables A,
B,
and C.
So this first line is nothing new.
We have integer A equals 28.
So A is going to store the value 28.
Then B is going to store the value of 50.
And so
these two pieces shouldn't be too new to you,
but
what about for this next line of code?
We have in
C equals Ampersand A.
So maybe first I'll ask what type is C.
What's the
variable type that C is going to be?
Yeah,
so it's going to be an end pointer,
an integer pointer,
and it's gonna store the address of A.
So as you can see here,
now the address of A,
which I just arbitrarily set as 0 X 12,
is now being stored in C.
Great.
So then this next line of code we have star C
equals 14.
So what
is that doing?
What is the star here doing?
And which variable is that going to change?
Any thoughts here?
Yeah,
exactly.
So A's value is gonna change.
Why is that?
So.
The star see.
Is the referencing the address stored at C.
And so the address stored at C
is our A variable and so it's gonna
use that address,
go to that address.
So
we see this address,
go to it.
And
then change that value to 14.
OK.
And then this next line,
we have C equals
Ampersand
B.
So I'm reassigning C's value
to the address
of B.
So we can see that here,
it's now changed to X X 13.
Oh
And then
this final line,
we have star C equals 25.
So similar to what we just saw,
I'm gonna go to the address store.c.
So go to X X 13
and then
set that
to 25.
OK,
any questions about this exercise?
These addresses are relatively arbitrary.
In reality they would probably
be
um.
Bigger numbers
farther apart,
um,
since these are integers and pointers.
Someone asks,
why would you use this um if you could set the value directly.
Yeah,
that's a great question.
And so,
um,
one example we saw yesterday in lecture was
the swap function where if you're trying to
Swap two values,
um,
you couldn't pass them in by value
because that wouldn't change those values directly
in a separate function like it's out of scope
and so when we used um pointers and referenced those,
then the pointers
um were able to change the values in the main function
even though
um
what happens in the function was going to be like not necessarily.
Remembered after the function was done running.
OK.
OK,
can pointers be used in a loop to change value of multiple integers?
Yeah,
definitely.
Why do you say C equals B,
but in C equals 8% A?
OK,
yeah,
so.
This line of code in C
equals Ampers and A.
Is just like
the ones before it,
right?
We're just declaring a new variable
instead of it being an integer,
it's gonna be an integer um pointer
and so
we're initially setting that value to to the address of A which is XX 13.
And then
When I do
C equals
A and B.
We're just updating the value.
So like I could have done
um like in or A equals 5 to update the value of A
the same way
we're just taking C,
which is a pointer,
and updating its value to a different address.
So in this case
the address of B.
Uh,
I see.
OK,
so someone asks when
C equals 25,
then is A also gonna change to 25?
Yeah,
that's a great question.
So,
um,
because I've updated
the address that's stored in C here
to the address of B,
it's no longer pointing
to the variable A.
Alright,
so now it's pointing to the variable B and so when I do this
de-reference,
and I set it to 25,
it's setting 25
um
for the B variable and not A anymore.
OK.
All right,
these are great questions.
And,
OK.
Hopefully,
uh,
more clarity will come in these next few
words.
Can a pointer point to two things?
No,
a pointer can only store
an address,
right?
One address.
And so
we did see that you can have
two pointers
storing the same address,
so that would mean pointing to the same
integer or variable,
but you can't have one pointer
that's pointing to two
things.
So that's a great question.
OK.
Can you make a pointer array?
Uh,
yeah,
just like any other
array of like integers or
um.
Floats,
you can also do that
with pointers.
OK,
we're going to keep going now
to talking about dynamic memory.
OK.
So
We were introduced to this idea of Mao and like
getting memory from the computer
and basically Malloch is like asking the computer,
Hey,
can I have this amount of memory allocated?
And so let's say we again have this
memory chunk here.
And
now I want to create.
In
pointer,
so an integer pointer
called
array per se.
And I'm going to set that equal to the address returned to me
from the Mao function.
So
Mao takes the input of how much
memory you need and so I'm going to say,
well,
I'm just going to store one integer for now,
so
give me
whatever the size of an integer is that much memory.
And so that's 4 bytes as we know,
and so we can see in the memory here.
We have our pointer called ray pointing
to
A block
of memory.
That's the size of an integer.
OK.
So that if I wanted
for more
integers here,
I can update my Mao call to be
Mao and then give me the size of an integer times 5,
that amount of memory.
So now we have
contiguous pieces of memory,
like one after the other,
and that's all pointed to at the beginning by the pointer array.
OK.
And so if I wanted to update
the first value in this array.
I can use the same dereferencing notation where I have
go to the address sort at array
and then set that to one.
So I'm gonna go to that first
uh integer slot
and set that to one.
What if I wanted to update
the value for the next
um integer.
What integer or what address comes after.
That
Yeah,
so we can do some pointer arithmetic here,
we can do.
Star,
so go to.
The address of array plus 1
and set that equal to 2.
Right,
so,
Instead of,
um,
because these numbers are just the addresses are just numbers,
we can also do some arithmetic to them.
So like you just add one
and we're gonna go to the next.
Right
Similarly,
we can kind of do this um.
With
3,
this next 3rd element.
And so you can also use this bracket notation
to refer to
the 3rd.
Um,
element in the array.
And
so on,
and we can update the next 1 to 4.
And so
Another thing we have to remember when we're working with memory like this
is that
we have
some
thing where we'remlocking,
so we're asking for this amount of memory from the computer.
And so I'm gonna say like,
here's this array pointer,
give me this amount of memory.
Um,
and then it's also important to know that we should always check
that that has is not null.
So if it is null,
there's nothing to do like the computer didn't have enough memory to give us,
we should return one.
Then we might use this array pointer somehow,
but at the end of that program we always
need to make sure that we're freeing this array.
Or freeing that memory that the computer has given us,
otherwise we're gonna run into some memory issues.
A few more memory errors that are pretty common just like the one we saw.
Is,
um,
what we just saw was failing to free every block of memory which we've maillocked.
So if I didn't have that free
call at the end,
then
that would be a memory error.
Failing to close every file we've opened,
so we're gonna
just,
we're gonna see in a second,
um,
working with files,
we also need to make sure
that we're dealing with that memory correctly
and also using more memory than we've allocated.
So this might be an issue you've already seen working with arrays.
If you have,
say,
an array of 5 elements and you try to access
um the array
element at the like 5th index or the 6th index,
that doesn't exist and that
is going to cause an error because you don't have access to that
piece of memory.
Yeah,
OK.
So we're gonna get into some practice here using pointers and using
Mao.
So
We're gonna write a function called concatenate.
It takes 2 strings
and returns a concatenated version of the 2 strings.
OK.
So I'm gonna move here to BS code.
Oh,
I restarted.
OK,
we'll restart it.
Someone says,
can we start array from index 0?
Yes,
you can index or arrays are always 0 indexed,
um.
OK.
OK,
so I'm gonna start out by
creating
um
So in here,
can create
concatenate.c.
And we're first gonna start by importing some libraries here,
so.
Um,
I know that I'm going to be asking the user
for 2 strings.
OK,
so I'm gonna include.
Oops,
CS 50.
H,
which gives us cat string.
Can include standard IO.H.
I'm going to include string out and
Standard.
Lib.
OK.
So I'm gonna start with this main function.
Um,
and if we recall,
I'm gonna take two strings from the input.
So,
I can say
my first string is gonna be
get string.
Whatever the user gives to me,
so.
Maybe like string one is
this.
And I'm gonna do the same thing
for a string
to.
OK,
right off the bat here,
what are some training wheels that I can take off,
given what we've learned this week about pointers?
Yeah,
yeah,
exactly.
String is a data type that we've defined
at CS 50,
but
in reality,
what we learned this week is that this is actually
a char star,
so it's a pointer
to a character.
So I can replace that.
And then we want to be returning our concatenated string,
so like
basically the first string after the next string in one string.
And that's gonna be whatever the result is of my function.
So I'm just gonna call my function cat
and it's going to take in.
S1 and S2,
so it's gonna take in two
pointers,
to
some strings.
And I'm going to store
this results in this 3rd string.
OK.
And then
finally I can just print
whatever I get here.
So I'm just gonna print.
S3.
OK,
so we've set up the part of getting in the input from the user
and calling this function that we haven't defined yet.
So let's actually define
that function.
OK.
So the first thing to note with
defining functions is what is my return type gonna be?
What am I returning?
Yeah,
that's true.
Which I can also write as a char star.
So I'm gonna say returns to Trustar
and then what are the types of my inputs to this function?
So you can see here that I,
I hope that it takes in an S1 S2,
yeah,
exactly.
So 2 pointers.
Each of Charar type,
so I'm gonna say it takes in.
One char star
called S1 and then one called S2.
OK.
OK,
so within this concatenate function,
we're gonna need to do a couple of things here.
So,
The first thing we're gonna need to do is
get the amount of memory,
so get
memory for this like 3rd string,
and how much
memory do we need
for this
string?
It's gonna be based on
the two strings that I get,
right?
2 Char stars.
And so,
I'm gonna get some amount of memory.
And then
that memory is going to be empty,
so I have to then
copy over
the values from
S1 and S2.
2 S3.
After I've done that,
then I can just return.
My new string S3,
which has
the
values from S1 and S2.
OK,
so let's
try this out.
So I know that I want to set up
HR star.
Of
S3 I'm gonna call it.
And I first need to get this memory from the computer,
so I'm going to use Matlock.
But then the question here is how much memory do I need to allocate?
OK
So I need
it to be at least as long as
my two
strings here.
Yeah,
so I need the size of these two strings.
So maybe I will actually get that first.
So I'm gonna say the length of the first string
and the length of the second string.
Does anyone recall how do we get this length of two strings or 1 string?
Yeah,
Sterling.
So this function
that I imported with string.
H here.
I'm gonna pass in
S1.
And that will give me the length of the first string.
I can do the same thing for the 2nd string.
So now we have these two values stored in here.
That helps us with allocating the right amount of memory here,
right?
So
How much
memory is gonna go in this Mao inputs?
What am I gonna,
how much am I gonna ask for?
Given that I now have
length 1 and length 2.
Yeah,
so it's going to be.
Length 1
plus length 2.
And the reason we don't have to necessarily use size up here
is because we know that the size of a character
is
just one bite.
And so I could
say like
length one times the size of a char.
But it's a bit unnecessary,
so I'm just gonna
stick with length 1 plus length 2.
Yeah,
someone asked,
what about the null character?
That's exactly right.
And so
we have to make sure that we actually allocate one more than these two lengths.
So that we accommodate the null character
and we make sure that it's copied over.
OK,
so now that we've allocated the right amount of memory,
now we need to copy over string 1 and string 2
into this new S3,
uh string.
OK,
so what
might I do here?
What might I use?
Yeah,
someone says string copy.
You could do that.
It's true.
For now,
maybe what I might propose is that we just.
Have a for loop
that copies.
We're gonna first start out with copying the first string over.
So I'm gonna start at 0 and then
I
How many times do I need a loop if I want
to go over every character in S1?
Some string length,
yeah,
length length one,
length one,
which is I have the length of my first string.
And then I'm gonna
do I plus plus,
great.
And so,
Here
I know that I want.
S3 some value in S3
to be updated.
Which index
Should go here,
what should I be indexing?
If I want like the first.
Value in S3,
then the 2nd character,
then the 3rd,
then the 4th.
Up to,
yeah,
people are saying I,
exactly.
OK,
great.
And then I'm gonna set this equal
to.
As ones
I value,
so.
Now I've basically copied over,
let's say if
my first string is um
the word.
Uh,
cat
Then
my C is gonna be copied into the first character of S3,
then the A,
then the T,
and then this 4 loop is over.
But then I still need to copy over
the second string.
So if my string 2
was
um.
House,
then I need
the 4th character of S3 to be H and then O then you,
then S,
and so on.
So I know I'm going to need another 4 loop here.
And I know that this is gonna loop
how many times?
Length too,
exactly,
yeah.
Great.
OK.
And then
now,
the index is gonna be a little bit different here,
right?
I can't do I again because
that's just gonna overwrite what I just wrote.
For the first string.
So how do I set up this index so that it starts
where
S1
ended?
Yeah,
I was saying lang one,
so that's the length of the first string.
Plus
I.
Yeah,
exactly.
So
if my first string was say 3 characters,
then
this would start at
the 3rd
index,
which is where the last one left off.
And then go
subsequently.
So I'm gonna
then set that equal
to S2's character.
OK.
Am I done here?
Am I missing anything from
S3?
Is S3 done
and ready to return?
Yeah,
the null character.
I need to include the null character so that
um my computer actually knows
when this string is stopping.
So at what index is the null character gonna be at?
Yeah,
the last,
the last.
Which is gonna be.
The length of the 1st,
yeah,
the length of the 2nd.
And so
that will give us
that final
index,
and we're gonna set that equal to.
Oops,
uh,
I said that equal
to backslash zero,
which is that null character.
OK,
and finally,
we can just return
S3.
OK.
Yeah,
I say I have to free,
so I maillocked this.
But I also have to make sure that I free it
and where should that free go is a quite a good question is.
Because I maillog it
for my S3,
right?
And then I'm returning
S3 to the main function.
And so I need it here when I print it,
so I can't give it back just yet.
So maybe I'm going to say here,
I'm actually going to free.
S3 after I've printed it,
after I'm done using it.
Then I can free up that memory.
OK.
So I think we can try.
Making it.
Let's see,
OK,
what error did we get here?
Called undeclared function,
uh,
rookie mistake.
What did,
what went wrong here?
What did I forget to do?
Header.
Yeah,
I forgot to prototype my function.
Exactly,
so
quick fix here,
let's see
if it makes this time.
OK,
looks good.
String one,
say,
uh,
David.
Maylin.
There you go,
and then prints out David Malan.
OK.
It's a great job.
Any questions about?
What we just did here.
OK.
OK,
great.
Um
OK,
so we have a few questions about why are we even
doing these things?
What's the difference between a regular variable name and these pointers?
And
so the main difference is really just that
um
the pointer
variation,
so like in Star,
Tartar,
those things are storing addresses,
not
like the values that we typically are seeing.
So those are pointing to addresses of variables that already exist.
OK.
OK,
we're gonna do another exercise here.
And it's gonna be less coding and more debugging.
Like what is gonna go wrong with
spotting some of these memory
issues?
So we're going to debug a program Create.c
that creates a file
given
as input at the command line.
So if I runcret test.c,
it's going to create a file called test.c.
But our code has 3 memory errors.
Can you find and fix them?
OK,
so.
And I come back here.
And
um.
We're going to,
where's my terminals.
Bring my terminal back here.
And I already have Create.c
loaded up here.
So let's take a look at what this is doing.
OK.
So,
it takes in a
command line argument here
as like the file name and so we're checking
did they actually include a command line argument.
If they didn't,
then we're just gonna print this error message in return.
Then we're going to get the length of the file name that they gave us.
We're gonna create a new block of memory to store that file name,
so
Chartar
called filename,
and we're asking for
the size of a char
times the length of our file name.
Then we're gonna check
if that Mao failed.
So if they didn't have enough
memory for us,
then we're just also gonna say Malloch failed,
return.
Then
we're gonna
copy
this
file name.
In a block of memory for the file name.
So sprint F.
yeah,
so we're copying whatever was inputted at the at the command line
into this newly created block of memory.
Then we're gonna open a new file,
so
we'll go in depth into open in a second,
but.
Open this new file.
We're going to write to it.
Or just have it open to be able to write to it,
and then we're going to check if that F open failed.
OK,
so right off the bat here.
Um,
we're missing a few things,
but we're gonna
run Valgrind here.
Bagrind
create.c.
Or
should we create?
And I'm gonna give it a
in command line argument of tests and we're gonna see what that gives us here.
OK.
So there's a lot of texts,
can be a little bit overwhelming to read,
but we can pick out a few things that might tell us what's going on.
So first we have an invalid right of size one.
OK.
And it's pointing us at
Line 16.
So they're saying,
OK,
something might be going wrong here.
We have
um.
6 bites definitely lost.
472 bytes still reachable.
OK.
So any ideas about what?
Issues we have
Someone says we are not freeing,
not closing,
and using more memory than we allocated.
OK,
so
with this free,
which
block of memory,
what variable do I need to free?
It's wherever I do.
Mallock,
so yeah,
file name exactly.
I need to make sure I free file name after I'm done using it,
so I'm just going to put it down here.
Free
file name.
OK,
and then we also are not closing
this file,
this new file that I have opened.
So I'm going to do Flo
new file.
OK,
and then using more memory than we allocated.
What is going on there?
Why do I need?
Why am I using more memory than I allocated?
So pointed us to line 16.
Where I ask for.
The size of a character
times the file name's length.
And that is the length of.
My file name.
Potentially
So if I have like.
A length of
someone,
OK.
Yeah,
not quite.
So someone says the size,
this should be size of Char star.
So we do want the size of a character since we're gonna try to store a length,
a string of length
of the file name.
But let's say my file name in this case was test.c,
right?
So that's.
TEST.
C 6 characters.
So this would return 6.
Is it correct that I only need 6?
Right to store that.
So
something that we saw
for in our
past.
Um,
program was that we,
yeah,
we actually needed
one more to count for
our null character at the end.
So if I update this to file name,
length plus one,
then that accounts for my null character.
So if I
make this again.
And we ran.
Create
test.c.
OK,
I'm gonna run
Valgrind.
And see,
now it seems like.
All heat box for free,
no errors.
And everything is well in the world.
OK.
So feel free to drop in the chat if you have any questions about this.
We're gonna finally move on to.
File IO,
so working with files,
reading,
writing,
opening,
closing,
all that good stuff.
So really,
we want to know here,
we're gonna work on this example of how might we copy
the contents of one file into another file.
So let's say for example we have
in.txt
as this input
text file
and then we also have an output text file that we want
whatever is in
in.txt to be copied to.
And so
those are the file names inex out dots.
We have like the file contents and then we also have
an address of the file.
So these two things
have their own addresses in memory.
Hi
So this first line of code here that we
got a peek of inslacreate
was
we have file input equals F open
N.XTR.
So it's a lot of
bits and pieces,
but let's break down.
What does that actually mean?
So input is the name
of
our pointer variable that we're creating.
File star is the type.
So
again,
it's a pointer to a file.
And then we're setting that equal to the return of F open
and F open is going to return
the address of
the
um file that you're opening up here
and so
you might wonder like how do we actually know what F Open is returning.
This is a good chance to read some of the documentation that we have
for functions like F Open.
And so this is an excerpt from CS 50's manual.
It's also linked
there,
um,
so you can feel free to go and read that,
but
It's a lot of
um it's a bit cryptic
but more or less this is saying
we have
file F open
and it takes in these two
inputs.
So the first input
is
a
char star,
so a pointer
to a character
that contains the path name.
So in the last example we had index TXT as that path name.
Then it also has this mode.
So
the mode
can be R if we're opening a file to read from it,
W if we're opening a file to write to it,
and A if we're opening a file
to a pended.
function returns a pointer to a file representing the open file
and in cases of error when the path name doesn't exist,
it returns null.
So it's all helpful information to know here.
Another note that we've already discussed a lot here that
string is actually just an alias for Char Star and so
these pointers
are,
um,
we've been using
for many weeks now,
but
Both represent the address of the first character in a sequence of characters
ending with the null character.
OK.
So let's say we we've now opened up
in that TXT
and we have this input
pointer
that's pointing to this file.
You can,
this is like a representation where
um each of these blocks is a bite.
And so
we have one bite for lowercase h,
then lowercase i,
then exclamation point,
and then our null character.
So how do we actually get that information?
How do we read it?
Well,
we can use F read.
So Fee takes in 4
inputs here.
And so what are those act what do those inputs mean?
Here we have
Ampersani,
so.
The address
of
C,
we'll talk about what C is,
size of character,
size of chart,
and then 1 and then input.
So what does that actually mean?
So the first thing
is.
A pointer,
so the address
of the first bite of memory into which to read the data.
So it's
some
address of a bite of memory
and that's where we're saying
OK you're gonna be reading from something
you should read it into
this
piece of memory.
Then the next one is size,
and so that tells us
the size and bytes of the type of data to read.
In this example we saw,
we wanted the size of a character.
Then we have
the number of those types to read at once.
So how many,
how many of the size blocks do you want to do you want to read?
In this case,
we just wanted to do one character at a time.
And then stream,
which is the pointer to the file that you want to read from,
in this case,
input.
OK,
this is going to return the number of items that we read
and so if an error occurs or if we,
the end of the file is reached.
Um,
then this function might actually return a value smaller
than
uh
than NME,
which is
in this case one.
So,
in this case,
it could either be 1 or it could be 0.
This would return 0 if there was nothing
to read.
OK,
so,
as a recap,
this is the location that we're reading from.
Which is
pointing to input.
This
refers to the size of the blocks that we want to read.
In this case,
one chart at a time and we're reading.
Yeah,
one
character lock at a time.
And then this
uh Ampersan C
is the location we want to store these blocks.
And so we've actually set up here.
A
character.
Um,
that's called C.
And this is gonna store one character at a time,
so it's gonna store each.
After the first F read.
And then
Once we have that stored and see,
how do we actually write it to a new file?
Or that we can use right.
Here the inputs are relatively similar
and so
we look at the documentation again.
It's pretty much.
Almost the same that we've just seen,
so it's gonna,
um,
instead of reading from or reading to a certain buffer,
which we call or this address,
we're gonna be
writing from that.
Um,
byte of memory,
and then we're specifying
how
big
in bytes the type of data is we want to write,
how many of those to write at once,
and then where we want to write to.
Again,
this function is going to return
number of items that we wrote.
OK,
so in practice we see
once I have this
C
but with
that has been read to.
Then I can output it
in this out.txt file.
And so
this is gonna continue again
and again we have
the inputs
reading I into C which is our buffer.
And then writing from our buffer
to output.
So on and so forth until we reach the null character.
So what we just saw visually
is what this piece of code does
in reality.
So you can see
we have opened in.
TT.
We're checking that it didn't fail,
then we're checking,
then we're opening out.tt also error checking.
And then
We create a character called C.
That's where we're
gonna be storing things.
It's gonna be our buffer.
And then
while F read
to the buffer C.
And we're doing one block at a time
from input while that is not equal to zero,
which means like while we're still
reading things,
while there's still things to read,
we should have right
from that character
buffer.
To
the output file.
OK.
That was a lot.
Any questions about file I opening
closing?
OK.
Why is this useful in real life for programs?
So,
yeah,
this copy example might not be the most useful thing we see here,
but
In other ways um it's helpful to be able to like write things to
files and read things from files
uh and you're gonna be doing a bit of that in
this week's problem that hopefully that gives you a better sense
um but you can imagine that
if you have like a very long
file to work with
or a very long
uh like lots of pieces of data that you want to be written to a certain file,
then it can be helpful to.
Use some code to do that.
OK.
OK,
we're gonna do one final exercise here.
And we're gonna create a a program
called PDF.C that checks whether a file passed in as a command line argument
is likely a PDF or not.
And so
something to note here is that PDF files,
they start with a 4 byte sequence.
So when you actually look at the bytes that are contained within
a PDF file,
it's gonna start with
this 4,
these 4 bytes.
OK,
so we're gonna
move back to BS code here.
And I'm going to code pdf.c.
OK.
copy over
some of.
These so I don't have to write them again.
But
we're gonna include
50.
H.
And then we're also gonna include standard in that gives us access to some
um
types.
OK.
So
I'm taking in a command line argument.
Which means I also should check that
they actually gave me
2 command line arguments.
They didn't give me 2.
Then
I'm going to print.
Uh,
improper usage.
OK,
and then return one.
OK.
So then once they've given me a file,
the first thing I should do is open that file,
right?
I want to be able to see what's in it.
I should first open it up.
So similar to the syntax we were doing before,
I'm gonna
have
a file pointer called PDF
and I'm gonna
open.
Here the first argument is the file name
and so
in this program I'm saying that the user is gonna give me
the file name in the command line argument.
So I can say RV1.
Right,
so if we recall,
PDF or PDF is going to be RV 0,
then the name of the PDF is going to be RV1.
I'm gonna set that.
In read mode so that I can read from it.
And then just like in their last example with that C character
that was our buffer that stored
the
thing that we read from,
we want to store
a buffer for these 1st 4 bytes as well.
So I'm going to use
this is a new type here,
but
it's a,
it's just another kind of integer here that is
typically used for storing things like bytes.
I'm gonna call this buffer
and
I'm gonna make an array of 4 bytes since I want to see those 1st 4 bytes of my PDF.
OK,
and since I'm also checking this against
these 4 bytes,
it might be helpful for me to actually store the sequence
here.
So I'm gonna call it
signature,
it's a PDF signature.
And
we're gonna put those values here.
Xerox 50
XX 44,
whoops.
And 0 X 46.
OK,
so now that I've opened,
I've set up my buffer.
Now I can read.
So,
I just want to read the 1st 4 bites.
So I'm not gonna put it in a loop.
I can also,
I can just read those 1st 4 bites.
I'm gonna read it to my buffer.
And then
I know that I want um
it to be.
One bite
at a time,
but
I want to read 4 bites.
And I want to read it from
this PDF file.
OK.
And then once I'm done reading it,
I honestly don't really need
this
PDF file anymore.
I've already gotten the information I need and it's going to be stored in buffer.
I'm just gonna close it.
OK.
So now at this point I've read
the 1st 4 bytes from PDF into
my buffer variable here in my buffer array,
and so
I can just check that
the 4 bytes that are in buffer
match up with this signature.
So
I'm going to loop.
I equals 0,
and I'm gonna loop 4 times since I know that I'm
just checking those 4 bytes.
OK.
And then
I'm gonna check bite by bite whether those two things
line up.
So
if
the I character or bite and buffer.
Is not equal to signatures.
Then
As long as there's at least one thing that's different,
I can say pretty confidently
that.
Print
Not a PDF.
OK.
And then I can just return 0 since we
did that successfully.
At what point do I know that I can return?
Like,
this is probably a PDF.
Ah,
thanks for catching that.
Yeah,
so if all 4 of these
are correct,
which means
as long as this if statement doesn't return 0.
And I go through this entire for loop,
then I can say.
This is likely
a PDF.
And then return 0,
oops.
Print
OK.
So we did that kind of quickly,
but are there any questions about?
I can try testing it out.
Um,
I'm gonna make a PDF.
Ah,
I forgot to provide an input to my clothes.
I want to close
PDF here since that's what I opened.
Let me make again.
OK.
So if I just run.
PDF it's gonna say
improper usage,
you need to give me a
command line argument.
Let's say I use create.c which we know is not a PDF.
We're gonna say not a PDF.
Cool.
Um,
I'm just gonna like create some
test PDF file here.
OK,
so now if I test.
PDF with my test PDF,
hopefully,
oh,
it says not a PDF.
OK,
in that case,
it might be that I have to upload my own PDF,
um,
but either way,
hopefully,
uh,
this
would work on a normal PDF,
but.
Um,
I'm not going to test it for now,
but you can try it on your laptop and try uploading a PDF and see if.
It
detects it correctly or not.
OK.
Any other questions about this program?
Well then,
with
that,
that's the end of
CS 50 week 4,
section 4 on memory.
Thanks for your participation in the chat and all your questions,
uh,
and hopefully I see you next week.